Well, if you woke up this morning
nursing a weird urge to learn about US
foreign policy between the two World
Wars and how that ultimately led America
into World War II, then baby, you are in
for a profound treat of serendipity
because that's what this video is all
about. So, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milt with a side of
isolationism, let's get to it. Well, all
right. After World War I and before
World War II, which is what we call the
inter war period, the US advanced a
foreign policy that promoted world order
while maintaining isolationism. And what
in the fresh heck does that mean? Well,
remember what I talked about in the
videos on the 1920s, namely that after
World War I, the United States wanted a
return to normaly. A large part of which
included isolationism from the world
affairs that created the conditions for
the First World War. In other words,
after years of being so extroverted on
the world stage, Americans just wanted
to turtle down and have some me time.
And that desire was a nasty egg in
Woodro Wilson's sock because he played a
big role in the peace agreement after
World War I. and his vision was for the
US to play a role in world affairs in
order to promote his vision of liberal
internationalism through the League of
Nations. But as you'll no doubt recall,
the Senate did not permit the US into
the League and thus Wilson got
positively woodroed. Anyway, that desire
for some national me time only deepened
during the Great Depression as is
reflected in Congress passing a series
of neutrality acts from 1935 to 1937
which made it much more difficult for
the US to get involved in foreign
conflicts. And these neutrality acts
were all the more important to Americans
since a group in the Senate called the
NY committee investigated the causes of
US involvement in World War I and came
to a disturbing conclusion. Namely, that
bankers and manufacturers of war
supplies had pushed the US into war in
order to make a profit from the
conflict, which you know, not the best
PR. But still, many of the findings of
the NY committee were unfounded and
without sufficient evidence. And yet, so
strong was the isolationist sentiment
among Americans that many simply
accepted that the conspiracy was true,
which ultimately led to the passage of
the Neutrality Act. Oh, and by the way,
if you want note guys to follow along
with this video and all my videos, check
that link in the description. Anyway,
the point is during the inter war
period, all signs seem to be pointing to
the fact that Americans were altogether
uninterested in getting involved in
global affairs. We just wanted to lay in
our bed, listen to folklore, and feel
our feelings for a while. But here's
where I tell you that that's not quite
the whole story. That's right. Despite
this push for isolationism, the United
States continued to involve itself in
international affairs in order to
promote a world order according to
American liking. And that occurred
mainly in three different ways. First,
US foreign policy makers continue to
influence world affairs through
international financial investment. And
the best example here is the DAW plan,
which was enacted in 1924. So, recall a
few videos ago when I told you that the
Treaty of Versailles, which ended World
War I, had slapped Germany with the
requirement to pay reparations to the
victorious Allied powers. And to put it
mildly, that requirement eventually
contributed to a near complete meltdown
of the German economy. And so, the
German government decided to solve that
problem by just printing more money. But
that strategy backfired and sent them
into a severe economic crisis known as
hyperinflation, which meant that the
German mark was basically worthless. And
just for funsies, let me press upon you
just how bad it got. Like right at this
very moment, if I flew my Hind parts to
Germany with a single US dollar and
traded it for a euro, which is the
currency Germany currently uses, then as
of this recording, I'd get.84 in return,
which is to say it's pretty close to an
equal exchange. But if I did the same
thing in November of 1923, then my
single dollar would get me 4.2 trillion
marks back. to which I say what the
point is the German economy was
basically circling the drain and that
created a big honking problem. You see
when Germany could no longer afford to
make its reparations payments to Britain
and France who relied on those payments
to rebuild their own countries it might
have started yet another catastrophic
war and so in a situation like that the
US even though deeply desirous of its
isolationist me time decided to get
involved in international affairs and
help keep the peace and that is what the
DAW's plan was for. It authorized
billions of dollars of loans to Germany
so that they could make their
reparations payments to Britain and
France. And with that money, Britain and
France could then make their loan
payments to the United States. And so in
this way, the US was able to center the
world's financial system on itself while
remaining politically neutral in
European conflict. However, don't forget
that when the Great Depression hit, this
whole system failed since all that sweet
American funding dried right up and that
created a domino effect that plunged
Europe into an economic depression as
well. Anyway, the second way the US
remained isolated but still attempted to
influence world affairs was through the
signing of international peace treaty.
For example, in 1928, dozens of nations,
including the United States, signed the
Kellogg Brand Pact, which formerly
renounced war as an instrument of
national policy. In other words, with
the guns of World War II still ringing
in everybody's ears, 63 nations got
together and were like, "Guys, let's
never go to war again, okay?" To which
global developments 10 years in the
future were like, "Aw, that's so cute."
But who's going to tell it? Needless to
say, the pact was more idealistic than
practical policy since it had no
mechanism for enforcement, mainly owing
to the fact that it was negotiated and
signed outside the authority of the
League of Nations. But the point is,
signing this treaty allowed the United
States to appear engaged in global peace
efforts while at the same time avoiding
military obligations. And finally, the
third way the US attempted to influence
world affairs while remaining neutral
was by engaging in selective military
interventions mostly in Latin America.
And here I'll just give you one example.
So in 1915, the US military occupied
Haiti after years of instability on the
island began to threaten American
economic interest and that occupation
lasted until 1934. And this occupation
was a direct extension of two
significant foreign policy commitments
from the preWorld War I era that had
effects into the inter war period. First
was the Roosevelt corollary to the
Monroe Doctrine which asserted that
countries in the Western Hemisphere were
required to behave in accordance with US
goals or else face military
intervention. Or if you want it real
simple, the Roosevelt corollary was
basically the Monroe Doctrine with a
gun. And then the second policy that led
to the occupation of Haiti was William
Howard Tass dollar diplomacy in which
the US made significant financial
investments in Caribbean and Latin
American economies. And ultimately this
was the means by which the US could bind
those nations independence to itself and
ensure that they acted in ways that
aligned with American foreign policy.
And so not surprisingly when American
financial investment was threatened in
Haiti the US military got busy occupying
it real quick. So in some between the
two world wars the US attempted to do
two things at once. First, it pursued
isolationism regarding world affairs so
that it wouldn't get involved in another
foreign conflict like World War I.
Second, it was still very much involved
in world affairs in order to shape
international politics according to its
liking. And so therefore, as World War
II broke out in 1939, this same tension
continued to pull Americans in two
directions. And in general, many
Americans opposed US military
involvement in the war, even though they
were concerned about the rise of fascism
and totalitarianism in Europe and Asia.
For example, the rise of fascism in
Germany under the influence of the Nazi
party got Americans real sweaty.
Although to be fair, at least near the
beginning of the war, a growing number
of Americans supported both Italian and
German fascism for attempting to
stabilize their respective economies.
But still, fascism drew out the flop
sweats of many Americans because under
the leadership of Adolf Hitler, Germany
rejected all the terms of the Treaty of
Versailles that had destroyed their
economy and slapped them with no small
amount of international shame. And it
became very clear that Hitler's
particular brand of fascism and rank
militarism was in no way content to
remain within the boundaries of Germany.
Now, Hitler started gobbling up
territory in Europe. And that
expansionism was, to put it mildly, real
concerning to Americans. And then
equally concerning, Japan too was
joining the fascism party. And in 1931,
Japan invaded Manuria in order to expand
its empire and gain access to valuable
natural resources. And by 1932, Japan
had built a puppet state in China known
as Manuko. And then they just continued
their policy of aggressive expansionism
from there. And therefore, these
developments really put a strain on the
American commitment to neutrality in the
war. However, the biggest strain on US
isolationism came when France fell to
the Nazis, which was a massive blow to
the Allied cause and an indicator that
Germany might be on the path to victory.
But even so, Roosevelt maintained the
US's stance of neutrality while
simultaneously finding ways to assist
Great Britain without making a formal
declaration of war. And these efforts
included Roosevelt's cash and carry
policy, which allowed waring nations to
purchase munitions from the US if they
paid in cash and transported the
supplies on their own ships. But
eventually Allied cash ran dry and so
Roosevelt shifted to the lend lease
policy which allowed waring nations to
borrow equipment to carry out the war.
Though there was kind of a wink to the
agreement since the borrowed materials
weren't actually expected to be
returned. And in order to protect Great
Britain's right to make these
transactions with the United States,
Roosevelt provided air and naval troops
to protect against German submarines.
And when Germans started attacking US
ships, it created an undeclared naval
war with Germany that created an even
heavier strain on US neutrality. But
what ultimately snapped that tension and
dragged the US into the war was the
surprised Japanese attack on a US naval
base in Hawaii, namely Pearl Harbor. So
on the morning of December 7th, 1941,
the Japanese Air Force bombed the base,
killing more than 2400 Americans and
destroying hundreds of fighter planes
along with eight battleships docked in
the bay. And in the blink of an eye,
public sentiment against US involvement
in World War II shifted entirely. And so
Roosevelt asked Congress for a
declaration of war against Japan and
received it since it became clear to the
nation that war was the only means by
which to protect freedom and democracy
against the existential threats of
fascism and totalitarianism. And because
Japan was formerly allied with Germany
and Italy only 4 days later they
declared war on the United States which
gave Roosevelt the pretext to declare
war on Germany as well. And that my dear
people is how the US got out of bed, put
folklore on pause and entered the world
stage ready to put a proper American
smackdown on fascist and totalitarian
states. And that is where we're going to
pick up the story in the next video.
Okay. You can click here to watch my
other videos from unit 7 or you can
click here to grab my video note guides
which will help you get all the contents
of this course firmly crammed into your
brain folds. I'm glad you came around
and I'll catch you on the flipflop. I'm
Laur.